I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
I know so many people
who have been diagnosed
with Alzheimer’s disease,
the most common
cause of dementia.
And I bet you do too.
In fact, more than six million
people in the US have it.
So how do we avoid becoming
one of those statistics?
That's a main thrust of
my forthcoming book,
How Not to Age.
But in the meanwhile,
here's a discussion of some
little-known risk factors in this,
our 300th podcast episode.
In our first story, we explore the effect
of pesticides on Alzheimer’s disease.
Although there is a growing list
of Alzheimer's disease
susceptibility genes, even if
you put them all altogether,
they account for less than half
of all Alzheimer's cases.
The single most compelling piece
of data on the potential control
we have over the disease
is the fact that if you have
identical twins, with the exact
same genes, even if one gets
Alzheimer's the other
usually does not.
So, we have to think
about all the other
contributing factors
beyond just genetics.
In my video on pesticides and cancer,
I talked about this study.
There’s a list of chlorinated
pesticides, including DDE
(a metabolite of DDT) that
are classified by the EPA
as probable human carcinogens.
But in the study, blood
levels of DDE and others were
associated not with
increased cancer mortality,
but increased risk of
other-cause mortality.
This led researchers to
speculate it may be due to
an associated increased risk
of diabetes or dementia.
I’ve talked previously
about the diabetes link.
What about dementia?
“Elevated Serum Pesticide Levels
and Risk for Alzheimer Disease.”
A research team at Rutgers found
significantly higher blood
levels of DDE in Alzheimer’s disease
patients compared to controls,
and autopsy studies
show blood levels
are a good proxy for brain levels.
Those with the highest levels
were at about four times
the odds of being
demented with Alzheimer's.
And in a petri dish, DDE increases
amyloid precursor protein levels
in human brain cells, providing
a potential mechanism.
Put all these studies together,
and there does indeed seem
to be a link, consistent with
data showing about a doubling
of risk for developing dementia among
those acutely pesticide poisoned.
Among U.S. elders, DDT and its
breakdown product DDE are also
associated with increased risk
of cognitive decline in general.
DDT was extensively
used in the United States
from the 1940s through the 1960s.
At its peak, we were churning
out 180 million pounds a year.
And it’s still in our bodies to this day,
contaminating the bloodstreams of
more than 90 percent of Americans,
and DDE, the pesticide
linked to quadrupling the odds
of Alzheimer’s, were at the highest levels.
It’s still in our bodies because
it’s still in the food supply.
In my last video on the topic,
I noted that the levels of
DDT, DDE, and other banned
pesticides and pollutants
were much lower in the breast
milk from a vegetarian mother
compared to breast milk of
her non-vegetarian sister.
And the largest difference
was noted for DDE,
which was four times lower
in the vegetarian sister.
These toxins build up the food
chain; so, it makes sense that
the most contaminated foods are
meat, fish, and dairy products.
5 to 10 times higher
levels in meat, eggs,
fish, and dairy than what
they found in plant foods.
And unfortunately, cooking doesn’t
destroy pollutants like DDE—
in fact it may make them
even more concentrated.
And this is for a pesticide
that may increase the risk
of Alzheimer’s disease as
much as if you carried
the so-called Alzheimer’s
gene APOE4.
In our next story, we look
at the role of meat
on Alzheimer’s disease.
What is behind the dramatic
increase in dementia
in Japan over recent decades?
Maybe it’s rising obesity rates
or the increases in cholesterol,
saturated fat, and iron,
or increases in animal products and meat.
Overall, calories just went
up about 10% in Japan,
whereas animal fat and meat
consumption rose 500%,
about 10 times the rise in sugary junk.
Now, during this timespan,
rice consumption went down,
but the thinking is that
rather than white rice
somehow being protective,
maybe they were just eating
something worse instead.
It’s like when you find fish consumption
is correlated with less disease,
you wonder if it’s because
they’re eating that
rather than some worse meat.
If you look across multiple countries,
you see a similar pattern,
with the most important
dietary link to Alzheimer’s
appearing to be meat consumption,
with eggs and high-fat
dairy also maybe contributing.
There appears to be a
really tight correlation
between Alzheimer’s and
per capita meat supply.
And, then, studies within
countries uncover similar findings,
with Alzheimer’s and cognitive decline
associated with meaty,
sweety, fatty diets,
whereas most plant
foods were associated
with risk reduction.
This could be for a variety of reasons.
Animal products tend to have
more copper, mercury,
lead, and cadmium,
and no folate,
but contain saturated fat and cholesterol,
and pro-inflammatory advanced
glycation end products;
so many mechanisms
that dietary modification
may be our best bet
for reducing risk of
Alzheimer’s disease.
But, how do we know
it’s cause-and-effect –
the evidence that meat consumption
is causally linked to Alzheimer’s disease?
Well, there’s the strength
of the association,
the consistency across
different types of studies,
the fact that the dietary changes
preceded the risk of dementia,
the dose response—
more meat linked to more risk—
a bunch of plausible mechanisms.
We know that meat is a risk factor
for other chronic diseases,
but there’s never been
randomized controlled trial
to put it to the test.
When you read reviews
of the damaging effects
of high-fat diets to
the brain and cognition,
a number of factors are proposed
to account for the high-fat diet-induced
damage to the brain.
Oxidative stress, insulin
resistance, inflammation,
and changes to blood vessels
and the integrity of
the blood brain barrier.
But, these are based mostly
on studies of rodents.
Yes, high fat diets can cause
energy dysfunction in the brain,
based on fancy MRI techniques.
With CT scans, you can follow this
intracranial artery stenosis,
this brain artery clogging, over time,
and follow the progression
from mild cognitive impairment
to Alzheimer’s disease.
Those who only had
low-grade stenosis
were pretty stable over time
in terms of their cognitive function
and ability to dress themselves,
and other activities of daily living,
whereas those with more clogging
started slipping over the years.
And those who started
out with the most
brain atherosclerosis
rapidly went downhill,
and twice as likely to progress
to full-blown Alzheimer’s.
Chronic consumption of
standard Western diets,
and rich in saturated
fat and cholesterol,
may compromise our
cerebrovascular integrity
compromise the blood
vessels in our brain.
So, of course, drugs are recommended,
“pharmacological modulation”
of diet-induced dysfunction.
But why not just try to eat healthier
in the first place?
Finally today, we look at
reducing glycotoxin intake
to ward off Alzheimers.
Each of us has about 6 billion
miles of DNA.
How does our body keep it
from getting all tangled up?
There are special proteins
called histones,
which act like spools
with DNA as the thread.
Enzymes called sirtuins
wrap the DNA
around the histones spools
and in doing so silence
whatever genes
were in that
stretch of DNA,
hence their name sirtuins,
which stands for silencing
information regulator.
Although they were discovered
only about a decade ago,
the study of sirtuins
has become one
of the most promising
areas of biomedicine,
since they appear to
be involved
in promoting healthy
aging and longevity.
Suppression of this
key host defense
is considered a central feature
of Alzheimer’s disease.
Autopsies of Alzheimer’s victims
reveal that loss of sirtuin enzyme activity
is closely associated
with the accumulation
of the plaques and tangles
in the brain
that’s characteristic of
Alzheimer’s disease.
Sirtuins appear to
activate pathways
that steer the brain away
from the formation
of plaque and
tangle proteins.
Because a decrease in
sirtuin activity
can clearly have deleterious
effects on nerve health,
they’re trying to
come up with drugs
to increase sirtuin activity,
but why not just prevent its
suppression in the first place?
Glycotoxins in food
suppress sirtuin activity-
these so-called advanced
glycation end products, or AGE’s.
Our modern diet includes
excessive AGE’s,
which can be neurotoxic.
High levels in the blood
may predict cognitive
decline over time.
If you measure the urine
levels of glycotoxins
flowing through the bodies
of older adults,
those with the
highest levels
went on to suffer the
greatest cognitive decline
over the subsequent
nine years.
As we age, our brain
literally shrinks.
In our 60's and 70's we lose
an average of five cubic centimeters
of total brain tissue
volume every year,
but some lose more
than others.
Brain atrophy may be reduced in
very healthy individuals,
and a few people don’t
lose any brain at all.
Normally we lose about 2% of
brain volume every year,
but that’s just
the average.
Although the average
brain loss for folks
in their 70's and 80's
was 2.1%,
some lost more,
some lost less,
and some men and women
lost none at all
over a period of
four years.
Researchers in Australia
provided the first evidence
linking AGEs with this kind
of cerebral brain loss.
So limiting one’s consumption
of these compounds
may end up having significant
public health benefits.
Because sirtuin deficiency
is both preventable
and reversible by dietary
AGE reduction,
a therapeutic strategy that
includes eating less AGE's
may offer a new strategy to combat
the epidemic of Alzheimer’s.
Some of these glycotoxins
are produced internally,
particularly in diabetics,
but anyone can get them
from smoking and eating,
particularly foods high
in fat and protein.
In a previous video I listed the 15 foods
most contaminated with glycotoxins,
mostly chicken, but also
pork, beef, and fish,
which may help explain why
those that eat the most meat
may have triple the risk of
getting dementia
compared to long-time
vegetarians.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.